Workmen's Circle Collection Workmen's Circle
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
Workmen's Circle
1931-1971
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
0.5 Cubic feet 1 Box
Appraisal note
This collection is very small and would not sustain an in-depth study of the local Workmen's Circle activity. The heart of the collection is the minutes of Branch 15 from 1952 to 1971, chronicling the declining years of the movement. These minutes are written in Yiddish. Younger students would be able to make use of the general, New York-oriented Workmen's Circle historical materials as primary source material.
Jewish immigrants faced many serious labor problems after their arrival in the country. They faced these challenges by developing fraternal labor organizations reminiscent of the Bunds in Europe. One of these many groups was the Workmen's Circle, or Der Arbeiter Ring, founded in New York City in 1900. In its early years, the Workmen's Circle provided extensive services for its members, including extensive medical care, burials, adult education, and children's schools and camps. As Jews became more financially secure, the Circle shifted its outlook from strident Socialism to a more moderate focus on creating a "better and more beautiful world."
The first Workmen's Circle branch in Hartford, Branch #15, was founded in 1901. At least a half dozen others branches were formed during the next two decades. In 1918, the branches joined together in the purchase of 297 Windsor Avenue (formerly the Aaron Club), calling themselves the Workmen's Circle Educational Alliance. (Windsor Avenue was subsequently renamed and renumbered; the property seems to have become 2003 North Main Street.) In 1927, the Workmen's Circle Ladies' Club formed, and in 1931, the Workmen's Circle Educational Center was inaugurated at the North Main Street property.
In 1953, the Circle sold the building on Windsor Avenue/North Main Street and relocated to 687 Albany Avenue, known as the Workmen's Circle Educational Center or the Labor Lyceum. This building was sold in 1965.
The date of the disbanding of the local circles is unclear at this writing. In 1971, branches 22 and 936 were dissolved and the members were transferred to Branch 15.
Anniversaries; Education; Organizations; Workmen's Circle
- Series I: Records & Manuscripts
  - Hartford/Branch 15/Anniversaries/40th and 50th Anniversaries, undated (Box 1)
  - Hartford/Branch 15/Board of Directors/Minutes, 10-1952 to 5-1966, 1952-1966 (Box 1)
  - Hartford/Branch 15/Board of Directors/Minutes, 5-1966 to 9-1971, 1966-1971 (Box 1)
  - Hartford/Branch 184/Anniversaries/30th Anniversary Banquet, 1938 (Box 1)
  - Hartford/Educational Center/Inauguration, 1931 (Box 1)
  - Hartford/Educational Center/Meeting Programs, undated (Box 1)
  - Hartford/Ladies' Club/Anniversaries/10th Anniversary Banquet, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Hartford/Mergers/Branch 15 Absorption of Branches 22 and 936, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Hartford/Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
  - National Organization/Anniversaries/40th Anniversary History, 1940 (Box 1)
  - National Organization/Anniversaries/40th Anniversary Publications, 1940 (Box 1)
  - National Organization/Conferences/48th Convention, 1948 (Box 1)
  - National Organization/Historical Highlights, undated (Box 1)
  - National Organization/Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Branch 15, 40th Anniversary, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Branch 15 members, undated (Box 1)
  - Ladies' Club (auxiliary), 1937 (Box 1)
  - Youth League, undated (Box 1)